Guide to the French Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
French Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection
1115-1941
MS 224
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(10 boxes, 1 folio)
An artificial collection of correspondence, manuscripts, volumes, and miscellanea relating to France, 1115-1941.
General note
Additions to this collection will consist of only materials printed or written in the French language, and pertaining to French life and culture. No items or portions of collections will be transferred from individial collections to this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of correspondence, manuscripts, volumes, and miscellanea relating to France, 1115-1941.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in four sections: volumes, correspondence and loose papers, miscellaneous, and oversize. All items that are not listed individually in this register--and this is the vast majority of the papers in the collection--are filed as "correspondence and loose papers in boxes 7-8. Most items are cataloged individually in the manuscript catalog, the union catalog, and the inventory catalog.
Europe; France -- Description and travel; France -- History; France -- Intellectual life; France -- Politics and government; France -- Social life and customs; Rolland, Adrian Nicolas; Delvincourt, Claude Etienne, 1762-1831; Castille, Joseph de Froment; Bertrand, Arthur, 1841-; Naville, Ernest, 1816-1909; Heemskerck, Jacob van
- Original accession
  - Volumes
    - "Recuil de pieces diaboliques pour servir a I'histoire'du temps"
      - Vols. 1-3, 1726-39 (Box 1)
      - Vol. 4, 1726-39 (Box 2)
    - L'Orphelin de la Maison de Tehau" (French translation by Premare (d. 1735) from the Chinese), 1731 (Box 2)
    - Rolland, Adrian Nicolas: "Philosophia a Domino Rolland in Collegia Be11ovaco", 1742-43 (Box 2)
    - "Ceremonial des Ambassadeurs, et Ministres etrangeres a la Cour de France", 1744 (Box 3)
    - 'Demoiresur L'Etendue de l'ancienne Rome, o par MD'Anville", [1756?] (Box 4)
    - Clement, Jean Marie Bernard (1742-1812): MS notes for his Du Genie de la langue francaise, [pre 1812] (Box 4)
    - Delvincourt, Claude Etienne "Cours de Droit Francaiseft, (1762-1831): (Box 4)
      - Vols. 1-2, 1805-07 (Box 4)
      - Vol. 3, [1807?] (Box 5)
    - Castille, Gabriel Joseph de Froment: "Catalogue de la bibliotheque", 1818 (Box 5)
    - Richer, [Edmond]: "Precis de l'histoire de Bretagne", 1821 (Box 5)
    - "Revolution de Juillet 1830": collection of 18 MSS and 3 printed items, 1829-30, 1860-65 (Box 6)
    - Bertrand, Arthur: MS concerning voyage on La Belle Poule, 1840 (Box 6)
    - Naville, Ernest (1816-1909): Histoire de la Philosophie, 1882 (Box 6)
    - Bruges, [Belgium]: Evenemens remarquables arrives pour la plupart a Bruges ano 621 jusqu'a 1477 (Box 6)
    - Heemskerk, Jacob van: Voyage a la Nouvelle Zemble et au Spilzberg dan le 1596 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and loose papers (see also Oversize)
    - 1360, 1444-1627, 1755-1899 (Box 7)
    - 1902-1941, no date, unidentified (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Papers of several French corsairs forced to land or take refuge in New Orleans which document Franco American diplom.atic relations, customs and habits of American maritime milieux, and slave trade of the period, Circa 1810 (Box 9)
    - Louis XV: signed document and engraved portrait in folio case, 1763 (Box 10)
    - Napoleon I: signed document and engraving of ...Ie mariage de L.L.M.M.C et R. in folio case, 1812 (Box 10)
  - Oversize
    - Marie Antoinette: two documents pertaining to her household, 1773, 1777 (Box 11)
    - Louis XVI: signed military commission and engraved portrait, 1786 (Box 11)
    - Lambesc, Charles Eugene de Lorraine: signed certificate, 1787 (Box 11)
    - Daubs, France (Dept.) Conseil: passport, 1814 (Box 11)
    - Louis XVIII: signed certificate, 1814 (Box 11)
    - Drouyn: diploma fromUniversite de France, 1820 (Box 11)
    - Araga, F. signed document, 1830 (Box 11)
    - College de France: reproduction of 1567 document with accompanying letter, 1903 (Box 11)
    - Binns family tree (photostatic copy), 1700s-1900s (Box 11)
    - Manuscript in Middle French, 1115 (Box 11)